Awaken to a World of Wonders!
Sleeping Beauty is a fantasy, animation, romance
film directed by Clyde Geronimi.
Cursed to die by the evil fairy Maleficent when she was a baby, Princess Aurora
is sent into hiding under protection from three good fairies.
As she grows up far away, Maleficent becomes increasingly
determined to seal the princess's fate.
Princess Aurora (voice), played by Mary Costa.
Prince Phillip (voice), played by Bill Shirley.
Maleficent (voice), played by Eleanor Audley.
Flora / Queen Leah (voice), played by Verna Felton.
Merryweather (voice), played by Barbara Luddy.
Fauna (voice), played by Barbara Jo Allen.
Sleeping Beauty is a 1959 American animated musical fantasy film produced by Walt
Disney Productions and released by Buena Vista Film Distribution.
Based on Charles Perrault's 1697 fairy tale, the film follows Princess Aurora, who was cursed by the evil fairy
Maleficent to die from pricking her finger on the spindle of a spinning wheel on her 16th birthday.
She is saved by three good fairies, who alter Aurora's curse so that she falls
into a deep sleep and will be awakened by true love's kiss.
The production was supervised by Clyde Geronimi, and was directed
by Wolfgang Reitherman, Eric Larson, and Les Clark.
It features the voices of Mary Costa, Bill Shirley, Eleanor Audley, Verna Felton,
Barbara Luddy, Barbara Jo Allen, Taylor Holmes, and Bill Thompson.
Sleeping Beauty began development in 1950.
The film took nearly a decade and $6 million (equivalent to $64,719,178 in 2024) to
produce, and was Disney's most expensive animated feature at the time.
Its tapestry-like art style was devised by Eyvind Earle, who was inspired by pre-Renaissance European art;
its score and songs, composed by George Bruns, were based on Pyotr Tchaikovsky's 1889 ballet.
Sleeping Beauty was the first animated film to use the Super Technirama 70 widescreen process and was the second
full-length animated feature filmed in anamorphic widescreen, following Lady and the Tramp (1955).
It was released in theaters on January 29, 1959, to mixed reviews from critics who praised
its art direction and musical score, but criticized its plot and characters.
The film was a box-office bomb in its initial release, grossing $5.3 million (equivalent to $57,168,607
in 2024), and losing $900,000 (equivalent to $9,707,877 in 2024) for the distributor.
Many employees from the animation studio were laid off.
Sleeping Beauty's re-releases have been successful, and it has become
one of Disney's most artistically acclaimed features.
The film was nominated for the Academy Award for Best Scoring of
a Musical Picture at the 32nd Academy Awards.
Maleficent, a live-action reimagining of the film from Maleficent's perspective, was
released in 2014, followed by a sequel, Maleficent: Mistress of Evil, in 2019.
The latter year, Sleeping Beauty was selected for preservation in the United States Library of
Congress' National Film Registry as "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
The film explores themes of witch, princess, magic, kingdom, fairy tale.
The tone is emotional.